<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lavvfulnesse of our expedition into England manifested</title>
            <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116853</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852068</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17371</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11672)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17371)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1394:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lavvfulnesse of our expedition into England manifested</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, first in Scotland, by Robert Bryson, and now reprinted in England, by Margery Mar-Prelat [i.e. Amsterdam, at the Cloppenburg Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A publication of the Scottish invaders.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed in Amsterdam at the Cloppenburg Press (STC).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
                  <note>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Durham (England : County) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Northumberland (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border, showing a lion rampant, a rose surmounted by a crown, and a unicorn</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>THE LAWFVLNESSE OF OVR EXPEDITION INTO ENGLAND MANIFESTED.</p>
            <p>Printed, firſt in SCOTLAND, by <hi>Robert Bryſon,</hi> and now Reprinted in ENGLAND, by <hi>Margery Mar-Prelat.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17371:2"/>
            <head>THE LAWFVLNESSE OF OUR EXPEDITION INTO ENGLAND MANIFESTED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S from the beginning till this time, we have attempted nothing <hi>preſumptuouſly</hi> in this great Worke of <hi>Reformation,</hi> but have proceeded upon good grounds, and have been led forward by the good hand of GOD, ſo now, from our own perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are we ready to Anſwer every one that asketh us a Reaſon of this our preſent <hi>Expedition,</hi> which is one of the <hi>greateſt</hi> and moſt <hi>notable parts</hi> of this wonderfull Worke of GOD, beſeeching all to lift up their <hi>minds</hi> above their own particulars, and without prejudice or partiality to lay to heart the Conſiderations following.</p>
            <p n="1">I. As all men know and confeſſe, what is the great force, of <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and how it doth juſtifie actions otherwayes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable, So can it not be denyed, but we muſt either ſeek our <hi>peace</hi> in <hi>England</hi> at this time, or lye under three heavie <hi>burthens,</hi> which we are not able to beare. Firſt, we muſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Armies on the Borders, and all places neareſt to hazard; for the defence and preſervation of our Countrey, which by our laying down of Arme, and disbanding of our Forces
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17371:3"/> ſhould be quickly over-runne by hoſtile, Invaſion, and the incurſions of our enemies. Secondly, we ſhall want all Trade by Sea, which would not onely deprive the Kingdome of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny neceſſaries, but utterly undue our Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rowes, Merchants, Marriners, and many others who live by Fiſhing and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities exported, and imported, and whoſe particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings are utterly made voyd by want of <hi>commerce</hi> with other Nations and Sea-trade. Thirdly, the Subjects through the whole Kingdome ſhall want adminiſtration of Juſtice: and although this time paſt, the marvelous <hi>power</hi> and <hi>providence</hi> of GOD hath keeped the Kingdome in order and quietneſſe without ordinary Judicatories ſitting, yet cannot this be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected for afterward, but all ſhall turne to confuſion. Any one of the three, much more all of them put together, threaten us with moſt certaine ruine, unleſſe we ſpeedily uſe the remedy of this <hi>Expedition.</hi> And this we ſay not from <hi>feare,</hi> but from <hi>feeling:</hi> for we have already <hi>felt</hi> to our unſpeakable prejudice, what it is to maintain Armies, what to want <hi>traffique,</hi> what to want adminiſtration of Juſtice, And if the beginning of thoſe evils be ſo heavy, what ſhall the growth and long continuance of them prove unto us, So miſerable a being, all men would judge to be worſe then no being.</p>
            <p n="2">II. If we conſider the nature and quality of this <hi>Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> it is <hi>defenſiue,</hi> and ſo the more juſtifieable. For proofe hereof, let it be remembred: 1. The Kings Majeſty miſled by the crafty and cruell Faction of our adverſaries, began this yeares warre, not we. When Articles of <hi>Pacification</hi> had been the other yeare agreed upon, Armes layed down, Forts and Caſtles rendered, an Aſſembly kept and concluded with the preſence and conſent of his Majeſties High Commiſſioner, the promiſed ratification thereof in Parliament (contrary to the foreſaid Articles) was denyed unto us. And when we would have informed his Majeſty by our Commiſſioners, of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and manner of our proceedings they got not ſo much as preſence or audience. Thereafter his Majeſty being content to heare them, before that they came to Court or were heard, warre was concluded againſt us at the Councell table of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and a Commiſſion given to the Earle of <hi>Northumberland</hi> for that effect: The Parliament of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> were alſo convocat for granting Subſidies unto this warre againſt us, as it not our: plots have been hatched, and military prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations made againſt us! many invaſions by Sea, which have,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17371:3"/> ſpoiled us of our Ships and <hi>goods:</hi> Men, Women and Children kil'd in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by his Majeſties Forces in the Caſtle: Our enemies therefore are the authore and beginners of the warre, and we defenders onely. 2. We intend not the hurt of others, but our own <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>preſervation,</hi> neither are we to offer any injury or violence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therefore have furniſhed our ſelves according to our power with all neceſſars, not to fight at all, except we be forced to it in our own defence, as our <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> beareth. 3. We ſhall retire and lay down our Arms, aſſoon as we ſhall get a ſure <hi>peace,</hi> &amp; ſhalbe <hi>ſatisfied</hi> in our <hi>juſt demands.</hi> Upon which ground even ſome of thoſe who would ſeem the greateſt Royaliſts, hold the warres of the Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> againſt the King and the Faction of the <hi>Guiſians</hi> to have been, lawfull defenſive wars, becauſe they were ever ready to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and quiet themſelves when they got aſſurance of <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> of Religion. Now this preſent <hi>Expedition</hi> being in the nature of it <hi>defenſive,</hi> hence it appeareth, that it is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but conſonant to our former <hi>proteſtations, Informations,</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrances:</hi> In all which, there is not one word againſt <hi>defenſive warre</hi> in this cauſe: but ſtrong reaſons for it, all which militat for this <hi>Expedition.</hi> Our firſt <hi>Information</hi> ſent to <hi>England</hi> this yeare, though it accurſeth all <hi>offenſive</hi> or <hi>invaſive warre,</hi> yet ſheweth plainly, that if we be invaded either by Sea or Land, we muſt doe as a man that fighteth himſelfe out of priſon. If a private man when his houſe is blocked up, ſo that he can have no liberty of commerce and traffique to ſupply himſelfe and his Family, being alſo in a continuall hazard of his <hi>life,</hi> not knowing when he ſhall be aſſaulted by his enemies who lye in waite againſt him, may in this caſe moſt lawfully ſtep forth with the Forces which he can make, and fight himſelfe <hi>free:</hi> Of how much more worth is the whole Nation: and how ſhall one and the ſame way of <hi>defence</hi> and <hi>liberation</hi> be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to a privat man, and diſallowed to a Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Thirdly, we are called to this <hi>Expedition</hi> by that ſame <hi>divine providence</hi> and <hi>vocation</hi> which hath guided us hitherto in this great buſines. We ſee the Expediencie of it, for the glory of GOD, for the good of the Church, for advancing the Goſpel, for our own <hi>peace,</hi> after ſeeking of GOD, and beging light and direction from Heaven, our hearts are inclined to it, GOD hath given us zeal and courage to proſecute it, abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and opportunity for under-taking it, Inſtruments fitted for it, unanimous reſolution upon it, ſcruples removed out of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17371:4"/> minds where they were harboured, encouragemets to atchieve it from many paſſages of <hi>divine providence,</hi> and namely from the proceedings of the laſt Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> their grievances and deſires being ſo homogenecall and a kinne to ours, we have laboured in great long-ſuffering by <hi>Supplications, Informations, Commiſſions,</hi> and all other meanes poſſible to avoid this <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:</hi> It was not premeditate not affected by us (GOD knows) but our enemies have neceſſitate and redacted us unto it, and that of purpoſe to ſowe the ſeed of Nationall quarrels; yet as GOD hitherto hath turned all their plots againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to effects quite contrary to thoſe that they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: ſo are we hopefull, that our going into <hi>England,</hi> ſo much wiſhed and deſired by our adverſaries for producing a Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall quarrell, ſhall ſo farre diſappoint them of their aymes, that it ſhall link the two Nations together in <hi>ſtraiter</hi> and <hi>ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er bonds</hi> both of civill and Chriſtian <hi>love,</hi> then ever before.</p>
            <p>And that we may ſee yet further evidences of a <hi>calling</hi> from GOD to this <hi>voyage,</hi> we may obſerve the order of the <hi>Lords</hi> ſteps and proceedings in this Worke of <hi>Reformation.</hi> For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at the groſſe Popery of the Service Book, and Book of Canons, he hath followed the back trade of our defection, till he hath <hi>reformed</hi> the very firſt and ſmalleſt Novations, which entered in this Church. But ſo it is that this backe trade lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth yet further, to the Prelacy in <hi>England,</hi> the fountaine whence all thoſe Babiloniſh ſtreame iſſu'd unto us: The <hi>Lord</hi> therefore is ſtill on the back trade, and we following him therein, can not yet be at a ſtay. Yea, we truſt, that he ſhall ſo follow forth this trade, as to chaſe home the Beaſt and the <hi>falſe prophet</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> and from <hi>Rome</hi> out of the world. Beſides, this third <hi>conſideration</hi> reſulteth from the former two, for if this <hi>Expedition</hi> be neceſſary, and if it be <hi>defenſive,</hi> then it followeth inevitably, that we are <hi>called</hi> unto it, for our neceſſary <hi>defence</hi> is <hi>warranted,</hi> yea <hi>commanded</hi> by the Law of GOD and Nature, and we are obliged to it in our Covenant.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Fourthly, the lawfulneſſe of this <hi>Expedition</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: if we conſider the party againſt whom: which is not the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> but the <hi>Canterburian</hi> Faction of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Atheiſts, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inians, Prelats,</hi> the miſleaders of the Kings Majeſty, and the common enemies of both Kingdomes. We perſwade our ſelves, that our brethren and neighbours in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will never be ſo evill adviſed, as to make themſelves a party againſt as by their <hi>defence</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of our enemies
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17371:4"/> among them, as ſomtime the <hi>Benjamites</hi> made themſelves a party againſt the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by defending the <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tachites</hi> in their wicked cauſe, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 20. We pray GOD to give them the wiſdome of the wiſe woman in <hi>Abell,</hi> who when <hi>Ioab</hi> came neare to her City with an Army, found out away which both keeped <hi>Ioab</hi> from being an enemy to the City, and the City from being an enemy to him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. As touching the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and Furniture of our Army in <hi>England,</hi> it ſhall be ſuch as is uſed among Friends, not among enemies: The rule of <hi>humanity</hi> and <hi>gratitude</hi> will teach them to furniſh us with <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries,</hi> when as beſide the procuring of our own <hi>peace,</hi> we doe good offices to them. They deteſt (we know) the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes of <hi>Nabal,</hi> who refuſed victuals to <hi>David</hi> and his men, who had done them good and no evill, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. And the inhumanity of the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> and <hi>Penuell,</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nyed bread to <hi>Gideons</hi> Army, when he was perſuing the common enemies of all <hi>Iſrael, Iudg.</hi> 8. But let the <hi>English</hi> doe of their benevolence what <hi>humanity</hi> and <hi>diſcretion</hi> will teach them; For our own part, our <hi>Declaration</hi> ſheweth, that we ſeek not <hi>victuals</hi> for nought, but for <hi>money</hi> or <hi>ſecurity:</hi> And if this ſhould be refuſed (which we ſhall never expect) it were as damnable as the barbarous cruelty of <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Moab,</hi> who refuſed to let <hi>Iſrael</hi> paſſe through their Countrey, or to give them bread and water in any caſe, <hi>Num.</hi> 20. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 11. and this offence the <hi>Lord</hi> accounted ſo inexpiable, that for it he accurſed the <hi>Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> and <hi>Moabites</hi> from entring into the Congregation of the <hi>Lord</hi> unto the tenth generation, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.3, 4.</p>
            <p n="5">V. The Fifth <hi>conſideration</hi> concerneth the end for which this voyage is under-taken. We have atteſted the <hi>ſearcher of hearts,</hi> It is not to execute any diſloyall act againſt the Kings Majeſty, It is not to put forth a cruell or vindictive hand againſt our adverſaries in <hi>England,</hi> whom we deſire only to be judged and cenſured by their own Honourable and high Court of Parliament; It is not to enrich our ſelves with the wealth of <hi>England,</hi> nor to doe any harme thereto. But by the contrary, we ſhall gladly beſtow our paines and our meanes to doe them all the good we can, which they might juſtly look for at our hands, for the help which they made us at our <hi>Reformation,</hi> in freeing us from the <hi>French,</hi> a bond of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>love</hi> betwixt them and us to all Generations. Our Conſcience, and GOD who is greater then our Conſcience beareth us record, that we ayme altogether at the <hi>glory of GOD, peace</hi> of both Nations,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17371:5"/> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the King, in ſuppreſſing and puniſhing in a legall way of thoſe who are the troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the fire-brands <hi>of</hi> hell, the <hi>Korahs,</hi> the <hi>Balaams,</hi> the <hi>Doegs,</hi> the <hi>Rabshakah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <hi>Hamans,</hi> the <hi>Tobiahs</hi> and <hi>Sandballats</hi> of our time, which done we are ſatisfied. Neither have we begun to uſe a military <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition</hi> to <hi>England</hi> as a meane for compaſſing thoſe our pious ends; till all other meanes which we could think upon have failed us, and this alone is left to us as <hi>ultimum &amp; unicum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medium,</hi> the laſt and onely remedy.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Sixtly; if the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall bleſſe us in this our <hi>Expedition,</hi> and our <hi>Intentions</hi> ſhall not be croſſed by our own ſinnes, and miſcarriage, or by the oppoſition of the <hi>English,</hi> the <hi>fruits</hi> ſhall be ſweet, and the effects comfortable to both Nations, to the Poſterity, and to the reformed Kirkes abroad: <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>med as at the beginning, the Reformation <hi>of England</hi> long prayed and pleaded for by the Godly there, ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their wiſhes and deſires <hi>perfected</hi> in <hi>doctrine, worship,</hi> and <hi>diſcipline,</hi> Papiſts, Prelats, and all the members of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Hierarchy, with their <hi>Idolatry, Superſtition,</hi> and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <hi>inventions</hi> ſhall pack them hence; the names of Sects and Separatiſts ſhall no more be mentioned, and the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall be one, and his Name one thoughout the whole Hand which ſhalbe <hi>glory</hi> to <hi>God; honour</hi> to the King, <hi>joy</hi> to the Kingdomes, <hi>comfort</hi> to the poſterity, example to other Chriſtian Kirkes, and <hi>confuſion</hi> to the incorrigible enemies.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:17371:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
